Hello, greetings. It is January 29th,
2026 and we're in Active Inference guest
stream 126.1
with Chris Fields, James Glazebrook, and
Maurice Dupree. So, thank you all
fellows for joining. First, Chris is
going to talk a little bit about the new
book and then we'll have a discussion.
So, if you're watching live, you can
write any questions in the live chat.
Thank you, Chris. To you.
>> Uh, thank you, Daniel. Um, thanks for
this opportunity for doing a a brief
presentation on um this new book by Jim
Glazber and myself on distributed
information and computation in generic
quantum systems. This was published by
Springer last November I believe or
December. So is available online.
And what I wanted to start today by
doing was just give a little motivation
of what we're doing in this book.
um
so that you can see once we get into it
uh why we're we've assembled the topics
that we've actually assembled.
So there are three main ideas here. Um
the first is that quantum theory is not
a very complicated theory about um the
motions of small particles. although
that's how it's typically presented and
it can certainly be used
uh to describe um motions of electrons
and atoms for example. That's what it
was developed to do from experimental
motivations.
[snorts] But in the last few decades
it's been recognized that quantum theory
is actually an information theory.
And so we're starting from the point of
view that quantum theory is actually a
theory of information exchange which
means it's a theory of how systems
prepare states and then measure those
states and we'll see that running
throughout.
The second main idea is that the free
energy principle which many of you will
be familiar with um some maybe not which
was developed 20 years ago as an idea in
theor theoretical neuroscience.
Um our second idea is that the free
energy principle is actually a practical
criterion for deciding whether any
bounded quantum system is persistent in
time.
And again this is not a new idea to us.
In fact, uh Carl Fristen, the originator
of the free energy principle,
uh published this perspective
and applied the the free energy
principle to essentially generic systems
already in 2019.
And the literature of the free energy
principle since that time has been
increasingly focused on the free energy
principle as a foundation a foundational
principle of persistence in physics.
And then the the third basic idea is
that active inference
um is a natural description of quantum
computation.
Active inference is the the picture of
behavior that one obtains from the free
energy principle. Uh active inference is
a combination of learning
and acting on the environment so as to
change its properties, its observable
properties. And if you think about uh an
organism or a robot that can act on its
environment, then one of the primary
kinds of actions it can take is just to
move around to go somewhere else.
So if I don't like what my environment
is doing to me here
um I can go to a different place and my
environment in that different place may
be different. So by going on vacation
for example I can alter how my
environment is behaving to me.
>> [gasps]
>> So this is a very kind of
um
also fairly standard idea.
Uh the term active inference was not
introduced until about 2010 by I think
Carl Frisman again. Um
but thinking of this as a way of
describing quantum computation is
somewhat new at least it
um our motivation here is that any
internal dynamics of a generic system
can be described in this way as a
combination of learning and action.
Um, now clearly this rules out some
things. For example, the idea of of a
system that passively observes its
environment is actually not formulable
within this theory. It's an idea that
doesn't make any sense uh because
actions are are always symmetrical
across boundaries as we'll see uh later
on. So, a lot actually follows from
these simple sorts of ideas. uh some of
which is in the book and of course it
motivates our more recent work and some
of this same thinking of course
motivates the work of lots of other
people besides us
in the physics community and the
biopysics community the cognitive
science and AI communities etc.
So let's start with this idea that
quantum theory is simple. It's not about
particles and waves. It's about
communication. So what does that mean?
It means that what quantum theory
describes
are agents
like us for example that set up
experiments that make measurements and
that communicate their results to other
agents. Now, this may be an odd way to
think about quantum theory because very
often quantum theory is associated with
what's called the microscopic realm.
Um, but that characterization is is far
obsolete. We know that quantum theory,
for example, describes black holes,
which are some of the biggest things we
know about in the universe.
Um so quantum theory is actually a
theory about exchanging finite
quantities of information between
systems and as we'll see uh it describes
all a systems as agents u in a very
clear sense
the theory tells us how these agents
work and what they can and cannot do
with finite resources. So for example
um a large number of what are called
nogo theorems follow from quantum
theory. Uh many of them are in a sense
variations on girdles and completeness
theorem.
Uh they tell us that there are a number
of things that quantum systems cannot do
with information.
Now the the basis for this point of view
is looking at at the theory top down. Uh
so instead of starting by postulating
the existence of things like electrons
for example
uh we postulate this the existence of
something that looks like a universe.
We ask what does it mean to say that a
system a small thing like me is embedded
in a big thing a universe
and the only characteristic of this
universe that's actually important is
that it does not have an environment. It
contains everything. So in a very
important sense it does not have a
boundary because it does not interact
with anything else. it contains
everything of interest.
So the theory uh then allows us to
address the question of how a generic
system embedded in a generic universe
interacts with the rest of the universe
which is its environment.
And it answers that question very
clearly and cleanly.
And it also allows us to ask what a
system can find out about its
environment. So what sorts of
information can a system extract from
its environment
and how can it change its environment?
So what kinds of information can it
transfer to its environment that causes
some change in its environment state as
perceived by it?
Now when we think this way
uh it allows us to personalize the
theory to recognize that it applies to
us.
And of course when one thinks of the
theory as applying to oneself,
uh one naturally connects it to concepts
from places like cognitive science. uh
concepts of computation, of inference,
of evidence
uh and so on. So
uh part of this move to quantum
information theory has been a move of
connecting physics to cognitive science,
artificial intelligence, neuroscience,
etc. Biology in general.
And that's reflected in the marriage
between quantum theory and the free
energy principle.
So the theory of the free energy
principle which everyone calls the FEP
also asks a few simple questions. But
the first question it ask is why don't
systems just dissolve into their
environments.
Uh why are there any systems that
persist through time that are
identifiable through time as the same
thing?
Um why doesn't the dynamics of the
environment just rip the system to
pieces?
Um so
if systems don't dissolve into their
environments then what do they have to
do to prevent this or just delay
uh being dissolved into their
environments
and quantum theory has an answer to this
question that can be formulated very
precisely. Uh it says a system can delay
being dissolved into its environment by
maintaining a weak interaction with its
environment
by maintaining sparse coupling in the
language of the FP.
It by not allowing the environment to do
anything really
uh surprising uh or large or damaging to
it.
And the FEP formulates this in
inferential terms. The FEP says if a
system wants to maintain itself.
Um it has to learn to predict what the
environment will do and particularly
what the environment will do to it. And
it needs to learn how to act to avoid
being dissolved by its environment. And
this is just active inference that I
refer referred to earlier. And it turns
out that these two questions that these
two answers to the question about
dissolution are basically the same. That
maintaining a weak interaction is what
allows learning and acting in a way that
avoids dissolution.
So it's weak interaction that allows a
system to be an active inference device.
So by putting these two concepts
together
it allows us to understand um what we
regard as interesting things and this is
what we try to do in the book. Uh it
allows us to understand how
any system divides its world into
objects that can be described and
manipulated. So why is it that when we
look out at the world, we see things
like laptops and other people and tables
and chairs and houses and animals and
plants and so on. Uh how does that work?
And in [clears throat] fact, quantum
theory lets us answer that question for
any system at all. Um how we can share
objects and communicate by them about
them. So for example, I'm currently
sharing this screen with you and we're
talking about it.
um how does that work? And again uh the
formalism allows us to formulate that
very clearly.
It allows us to understand why we see
objects and relation as embedded in
spacetime.
So why is it that when we look out at
the world, we see things organized in
space and we see events happening in
time. Uh those are very fundamental
questions and uh quantum theory lets us
answer them
uh under the condition that we're
talking about a persistent system. So a
system that complies with the free
energy principle. And finally the theory
lets us um
say some very detailed things about what
we or any system cannot know about
itself or its environment. So these
[clears throat] are the sort of
questions that we take on in this book.
And at this point I'm going to end this
little um slide presentation
and um
shift back to
um
the main screen and actually bring up
the book. so that we can talk about it.
So now let me [snorts] do
[snorts]
>> Thank you. We see it.
>> Great. So, um there's the book and we
can just kind of
[snorts]
page through this and um talk about
what's in it. Jim, would you like to say
a few things at this point?
>> Well, let's [clears throat] see.
Where are we going to start?
>> Yeah. Um
one
should we run through the introduction?
>> Um sure. Um
actually the introduction says many of
the things that I
>> Yes. Yes. And I think so
>> we we we start the book with the usual
sort of preface saying what it's about
which is is sort of what I've said. Uh
we we go on about um the transition from
thinking of quantum theory as a a theory
of particles to
um thinking of quantum theory as an
information theory
which as I said is is
sort of started happening in about 1970
with people like John Wheeler and
Richard Fineman as the major drivers
>> and is now a very large community a very
large effort and it's what allows the
concept of quantum computation.
So, um it's
a a change of perspective that actually
has enormous um potential technological
consequences
and and economic consequences.
I think we could go into chapter two and
the main points there
um include
uh the concept of um
uh quantum reference frames which
permeates through a large part of the
book. And um
that starts in uh 2.4.
Um but Chris, do you want to um comment
on what comes before that?
Well, what comes before that is really
um just a discussion of how one can
represent
the relationship between any system in
its environment. And actually, let me
just click up to this picture.
Um this is a picture that we've been
using for several years now to
understand how to represent the
interaction between uh two generic
systems one of which we regard as the
environment of the other
>> and you can see that this is perfectly
symmetrical. So uh we can switch these
labels system and environment without
changing anything.
And that to look forward has a a large
consequence.
Uh it tells us that the free energy
principle itself is completely symmetric
and that if we treat any entity as an
agent as the cognitive system then we're
forced to treat its environment as being
an agent also. So a cognitive system. So
that means that if I'm a cognitive
system
to be consistent, I have to think of my
environment as a cognitive system
because it's a system that I'm
communicating with. It's trying to talk
to me and I'm trying to talk to it and
we may be speaking very different
languages which we'll get to when we
talk to about quantum reference frames.
But just to focus on this picture in a
minute, it um the theory allows us to
describe the boundary between any two
systems
um as just a collection of quantum bits
and the systems interact by alternately
preparing and measuring these quantum
bits.
So this is um
literally a communication process with a
finite number of informationbearing
systems in between.
And um
this allows us to think of any
interaction as communication over a
channel in in basically exactly the way
that Shannon thought about it in the 40s
except here we're dealing with um
quantum processes not classical
processes.
>> I think how it works. [snorts]
>> Go ahead. I was going to say as
um
a a basic definition for the sake of the
audience, the quantum reference frame is
um a mapping from quantum states to a
pro a complex probability distribution.
And
um
quantum reference frames incorporate an
I a sort of a um a clock idea
that involves memory.
And
this is described in section 2.5.2. And
in particular the diagram figure 2.4 on
page 26. it. I don't know if you want to
uh leap forward to that now, but um
>> one sort of um embracing idea of the
quantum reference frames
>> is this picture that you're thinking of
or
>> no a 2.4 where where where you have uh
basically
um the memory
using a clock.
>> Oh, this picture. Yes.
>> Yes. Yes. I I think that that's an
important uh picture from us. And the
fact is as we go through descriptions of
quantum reference frames and how they um
figure and
they're of paramount importance as far
as the book is concerned
um
to an extent um these descriptions are
uh equivalent. They can start off at
this very basic generic level as as I
said a map between quantum states to
complex probability distributions or a
suitable framing of such to uh
a complex probability
um distribution.
But they can be tuned up from there. Um
to
various uh uh levels.
Um but we discuss later in the book
perhaps a bit too premature to discuss
that now. But one of the basic ideas
driving these is uh the idea of
reference and pointer states [snorts]
which you'll find on um page 28 2.6.
um
how you have this relationship between a
a system
uh reference frame
>> and um a point and point states.
>> Yeah, this is one of my favorite figures
of all time. Of course,
>> let me jump in here for us.
>> Well, thanks Chris for producing it in
the first place. Um,
maybe you'd like to uh comment on that.
I hope I'm not going too quickly through
chapter 2, but thinking that we have an
hour at our disposal.
Um, I think we should, you know, try to
speed read in a sense certain uh there.
So, uh Chris,
um maybe you could uh comment on that
and that would bring us up to
um
um at OCC's local operations classical
observers
um which is also highly significant in
what in [snorts] what follows.
>> Yeah. Let me give a a brief kind of um h
historical background here.
In classical physics, we have the
concept of a reference frame which is
something like an xyz axis for example
and it was always viewed as an
abstraction.
And in the 70s,
uh, businesses started to realize that
reference frames had to be physically
implemented. [snorts] And that means
that all reference frames are quantum
systems.
And so um even things like rulers and
clocks which serve as reference frames
are physical systems that have physical
properties that have to be taken into
account when talking about measurement.
And
it's only a a short leap from there to
realize that to use a meter stick
um
the scientist or the the system using
the meter stick me I have to have some
notion of what length is. So I myself
have to be a reference frame for length
or the little tick marks on the meter
stick don't make any sense to me. And
similarly if I'm going to read a clock
um I have to actually be a clock
otherwise the changes in the clock
aren't going to mean anything about time
to me. If I have no sense of time the
clock is meaningless.
So it becomes clear that
um systems that operate as as observers
have to actually incorporate these
reference frames into their dynamics and
it's these internal reference frames
that give our measurements meaning.
[snorts] So with that comment uh what
physically is a reference frame? It's
part of the dynamics of the system that
you're working with. What does the
reference frame do? It enables us to
make measurements.
And what this this picture illustrates
is that the process of making a
measurement always has two parts.
[snorts] Physicists traditionally talk
about measuring the pointer states of a
system. And that's a reference back to,
you know, the gauges from the old days
that actually had a pointer that moved.
And um
but in talking about measuring the
pointer states, one assumes
that one knows what the system the
pointer state is a pointer state of is.
But in fact, we have to ask how did you
find that out? How do you know uh what
system you're measuring?
And I like to use the the example of
sending a naive person into a crowded
laboratory with lots and lots of stuff
in it to read the value on a particular
voltmeter. Now, the first thing that
person has to do is find that voltmeter.
So they have to go in the lab and look
around and use some criteria that you've
given them to find the thing that
they're supposed to make a measurement
of. So to make a measurement, first one
has to find the device, find the system,
and then one can look at its pointer
state. And here I've just illustrated
that with this uh old-fashioned looking
box that has a switch and two dials.
uh before you can make sense of the
pointers on the dials and the pointer on
the switch, one has to actually find the
device
uh in an environment that typically is
very cluttered. I mean, if we think
about the environments that humans
operate in or any other organisms
operated in, they're full of things
and we have to have a a means of finding
the ones that we're interested in if
we're going to talk about the results of
measuring those things.
So, um, go ahead, Jim, if you want. We
can move on to lock protocols and talk
about
>> Yes, I think so. But I I just want to
say to
>> um kind of herald in what comes later.
I'm going back to figure 2.3 that we
have a criteria for um
um the commute possible commutivity or
non commutivity [snorts]
of
quantum reference frames
um which is of fundamental importance.
Um I thought I would mention that now
because when Chris comments further um
this commutivity or non-commutivity
uh issue um has a number of farreaching
uh consequences
and um this even turns up in the case of
um LOCC
local operations, classical
communications
and various issues about
um
the problem of sharing and
quantum reference frames, QRFs,
um the obser observability
and
see and
>> the many un questions of undecidability
that uh we address here. Um
maybe Chris you could just give an
outline of the basic idea following
say 2.6
pages 30 31.
>> Yeah let me see if I can find that. Um
and we also
as you know devoted
yeah okay this is the basic idea of
lock. Um, we have an entire chapter in
the book on this issue that Jim has
brought up about whether reference
frames commute
u, and the phenomenon that it induces
which is typically called contextuality.
And it it's probably best to understand
that in the
when thinking about two observers
interacting with a joint environment.
That's what this picture shows in a in a
very abstract way. If you think of two
observers, Alice and Bob, who are
separate,
they're interacting with an environment
that they share, which here we've
labeled E.
And one can think of them communicating
in two different ways. U one of which is
to jointly manipulate some system. So
they may be uh manipulating
uh a device of some kind in the very
classical or I shouldn't say classical I
should say canonical case uh for which
lock protocols were originally
described.
Um Alice and Bob are manipulating an
entangled pair.
Uh so two systems
in an entangled state. So they may be on
opposite sides of the world
uh manipulating this shared uh entangled
state
and at the same time they're
communicating classically u they're
saying I'm making this kind of
measurement. I'm using this kind of
device.
uh make sure you're using this kind of
device also.
Um and then they're sharing their
results. Um
Alice may in the in the case when
they're they're sharing an entangled
state and each making a sequence of
measurements of copies of this state. Um
they will then afterwards share their
results and discuss whether they their
results give them evidence of
entanglement.
And
um that what counts as evidence of
entanglement is formalized by
statistical tests that were originally
developed by Bell and Koken and Specker
back in the u 60s.
So uh this is all very well established
as technology
and um
probably very soon we'll be interacting
with things like our banks via protocols
that involve sharing entangled states in
this way uh because they're
communication protocols that are very
resistant to easedropping.
So these u these kinds of protocols are
are extremely important technologically.
>> I think we could also add here which is
taken up later in the book chapter 7 I
think that uh any such protocol
functions as a quantum error correcting
code.
Um so
this um yeah
>> has um pointers to um a number of things
which we do discuss later
um relative to quantum uh information
but
also
to questions of the nature of spaceime
and geometric phase.
something we have taken up quite uh
recently. Uh anyway, as we say that is
discussed in greater depth in chapter 7,
but I thought I would mention it now
since uh Chris was talking about um
protocols
um cryptography
um and such things. Um
>> well actually this diagram is a a good
place to introduce that. Um you can see
here
>> yeah we've depicted both of the
communication channels as extending into
the environment.
So uh think about what we're doing right
now. Uh we are communicating
uh via a physical system uh which is the
internet [laughter]
as implemented by lots of fiber optics
and lots of computers and and lots of um
energy sources and so forth that's
extended around the planet.
And even though at this point um we're
thinking of what we're doing as as
classical communication,
um many of the devices in that internet
uh depend for their operation on um
quantum theory working the way it does
such as all of the transistors and all
of the computers etc.
And so in doing this communication
process, what we're doing right now, we
are depending on this channel in our
environment being reasonably free of
noise
and it being able to correct
errors that come up in the process.
And uh all classical computer systems,
all classical communication systems rely
on various kinds of error correction
because all physical systems can fail.
And the environment at large
uh is always acting on these physical
systems that we use as communication
channels.
uh for example their power failures and
things like that and the internet is
designed to cope with that.
So we rely in all of our communicative
activities on the environment
implementing ways of preventing errors
from occurring in our in our
communications.
And this is formalized in the notion of
a quantum first in the notion of a
classical error correcting code and and
then in the notion of a quantum error
correcting code.
And a quantum error correcting code is
just a way of preventing decoherence.
You may have heard the term decoherence
which means the destruction of quantum
information.
um effective destruction of quantum
information by spreading out too much in
the environment so that people can't use
it. So if our quantum channel has too
much deco,
there's what we will see as noise
because the information we're trying to
share is leaking out into the
environment and not being replaced. An
error correcting code is a way of
preventing leakage and replacing any
information that does leak out.
>> Yes. And connected with this is um the
relationship of um
QEC with um um entanglement entropy
um which to an extent is behind what
Chris is explaining.
Um that that that that comes um a bit
later and
um that is significant in relationship
to [snorts]
um
um space time
energy momentum.
And one could think of a
triangle relating
um
entanglement entropy
energy momentum
Einstein's equation
embraced by uh geometry but as I say
that that comes later in the book. Um,
>> yes. So, see, we're we're still in
chapter 2.7
that discusses the nogo theorems for
generic quantum systems.
In particular, we have theorem 2.7.1
there. I don't know. Do you want to
comment on that, Chris?
>> No. Let me see if I can find it here.
Yes. Okay. This is uh as I said we're
still in chapter two. We're sort of
we're going this chapter introduces the
topics that the rest of the book is
going to be about.
Uh so for example er error correcting
codes quantum communication pathways
uh emergent spacetime and so forth.
Uh this last section in in chapter two
um introduces the idea of no-go
theorems.
Um the first no-go theorem
um
was Bell's theorem u published in by
John Stewart Bell in uh the 1960s.
Um the second one was the Kok and
Specker theorem published by U Koken and
Specker also in the 1960s.
And what Bell's theorem effectively says
is that
um
consistency with quantum theory
requires us to give up one or both of
two classical ideas. One of the
classical ideas is that everything
happens locally.
And the other classical idea is that um
states that are not being measured
nonetheless have determinate values.
And those are both um as you'll
recognize kind of key notions of what we
think of as the classical world. things
happen locally and even if you're not
looking at it, the moon is actually
there.
Um the Cook and Specker theorem
basically tells us that the context in
which we make a measurement always
matters
and that by altering the context, one
can alter the measurement outcome and
these theorems are almost equivalent.
Um but since that time since the 60s uh
a number of other theorems have been
proven about what quantum systems can
and cannot do and what they can and
cannot know. And this um theorem that we
put in chapter 2
is a summary of some of the things that
um quantum systems including us uh can't
determine by making observations.
So um for example
um we can't tell by making an
observation
how our own reference frames work.
we're using them to make the
observation.
So by that process of using them uh we
cannot tell how they work. Uh we can't
even tell what their input output
functions are.
So if you think about that one
implication is that we cannot by using
language fully understand language
and that's very close to Girdle's
theorem. It's very close to points that
Ludvig Vickenstein made and other
philosophers of language made in the
middle 20th century.
So the second part of this theorem is um
that
an observer can't determine using a
reference frame i.e by making an
observation
the the full properties of any other
observational capability of that
observer. So I can't for example using
language
um fully describe what my visual system
does.
Um, the third one here is that if I'm
talking to you,
I can't completely characterize the
language you're using to talk to me.
Um, and in a sense that's obvious,
right? I can't see your internal
processes. I can just see what you tell
me. I can just see what's encoded on the
boundary that separates us.
uh the boundary that we earlier
represented by an array of cubits.
So systems can't determine that they're
sharing the same language.
And actually that was a point that the
philosopher um Lyn Venorman Quin made in
the late 50s
um in in thinking specifically about
language. Um but this applies to any
kind of measurement or communication
protocol at all.
[snorts] And um this last one
says that
um
again that I can't completely determine
your language in a sense. Um
two systems can't completely um
determine what each other are doing.
Now
Jim mentioned entanglement entropy
earlier. Uh entanglement entropy is a
measurement of how much there
entanglement there is in a system. And
the second theorem that we have here is
I think one of the most important no-go
theorems in the book.
>> Um it's a theorem that says that a
system cannot measure the entanglement
entropy across its own boundary.
So for example, I cannot uh make a
measurement
that directly examines the internal
state of my entire environment or the
internal state of me
and compute the entanglement entropy
between them. No system can do that.
This has the consequence that no system
can know that it has not in fact
dissolved into its environment. So no
system can know that it is in fact
separate from its environment.
So from a kind of cognitive science
point of view, u that's a very important
theorem from physics.
Uh that systems can't determine that
they're actually separate from anything
else.
[clears throat]
So that's that's the the end of this
first section that sets up everything
else in the book.
And um
let me just comment that the entire
third chapter
lays out how in in great detail a
category theoretic representation of how
quantum reference frames work. And it's
this chapter that um explains the
conditions that Jim mentioned earlier
for whether quantum reference frames
commute.
And I think a a an interesting thing
about this chapter is that it connects
the physical notion of commut
commutativity between operators
which originally appeared in
Heisenberg's uncertainty principle. the
lack of commutativity between position
measurements and momentum measurements
or energy and time me measurements to
the mathematical notion of commutivity
that's defined within category theory
which is the idea of multiple paths
leading to the same outcome
and u systems don't commute
precisely when multiple paths don't lead
to the same outcome. So you can see
intuitively how communicates
to context dependence.
Uh it's when you change contexts in
midstream
that uh paths will not lead to the same
outcome.
>> So uh Jim, we have about 10 minutes to
go. Would you like to focus on any other
particular section in here?
Um
well I would say
oh um chapter 4
which is um
about the classical FEP and hierarchal
basian influence
and the mark of
blanket concept is introduced there
um which we generalize in a sense to
that of a holographic screen.
Um
maybe a lot of chapter 4 is already
familiar
to the audience. Um then
[snorts] well chapter five CCDs and
contextuality. Well, that's basically
about
um
well um the non commutativity of the
CCDs um
generates
um kind of um quantum contextuality
and we have our approach there. I I I I
would say
Um you know six and seven [laughter]
are really very significant and
particularly when we um
advance these ideas to the notion of um
um topological
quantum field theory
and from that incorporating spin
networks into topological quantum neural
networks. So, um there's much of the
book left um that might warrant a
separate discussion if um
Chris Daniel if you're interested.
>> Let me
herculan task for me in 10 minutes to
explain the rest of the book.
as as what we're doing here
>> along with the appendices. So
>> I think how far we've gone this morning
is actually quite good because we've
laid a foundation for
um studying quantum reference brains and
how they're going to appear time and
time again later. how they are
identified with topological quantum
field theories and um how they figure in
um um LOCC
and as I said the the issues of problems
of sharing the QRFs
and to determine well um what is the uh
in entanglement and generally these
questions are undecidable.
um
uh if uh not impossible to tell and I
suppose this is one of the basic
mysteries
of the subject and I think one tries to
dig deeper um
it's a mystery of nature
when when Richard Feman said nobody
understands um quantum theory
um he tried to work the theory out for
himself using the path interval
formulation.
I I I wonder if he was actually aware of
these deeper issues like contextuality
and problems of selfre referentiality
um
you know analogous to God's theorem that
um influenced Steven Hawkins way of
thinking in his latter years that
physics is essentially incomplete
and mathematics too because of God's
theorem. So trying to get to the point
what is it that nature is telling us
um beyond
these facets of um quantum theory um
non-locality
uh entanglement
um and such things that just end up
being undecidable in many cases as as
far as we're concerned.
Um, so maybe that
was the thing that Bman had in mind.
What is it in nature that causes all of
this? And I don't as yet uh fully
understand that. Um I think it's a a
separate issue, but um
let's see. Um we've reached it now.
Danielle, how would you like to proceed?
Would you consider a follow-up
discussion at some other time for the
rest of the
>> We can definitely do that
>> because there are a number of things
there that will be of great interest to
the active
um your active in inference u colleagues
um that very much relate
um to what um we're saying here and we
haven't really got onto the quantum free
energy principle yet. I think it's been
discussed before. It's there in the book
if anybody wants to read it, but I I
think that might warrant that chapter
and some ensuing chapters would warrant
a followup. Chris, do you think it's a
good idea?
Well, I I I think we might well want to
um
do something that
um sort of picks up from where we've
left off here. And uh we could talk
about the the quantum version of the
free energy principle and how it
distinguishes what's distinct between it
and and the classical version. I mean I
think u
say right right here because it's the
title of chapter five that uh the big
distinction is that
the classical free energy principle has
no natural way of dealing with the sorts
of context shifts
that quantum theory introduces
uh and that cause uh different
measurement operators to be
incompatible. non-commutative.
And so a major motivation for
introducing a quantum version of the
free energy principle is to be able to
deal with these issues of contextuality
and non-commutivity.
But to pick up on what you're saying,
Jim, I think that um doing something in
the future that actually focuses on um
the relationship between
communication uh QECC's and spacetime
uh could be of of great value here. And
I I think you just gave a beautiful
sort of explanation of of Fineman's
statement about quantum theory. And and
I agree with you. I think that that
[snorts] what he was probably expressing
was that um
one one can study the world as much as
one likes and it's still surprising.
>> Yes. And hard and hard to understand.
You're going to keep getting surprised
until you are not.
>> Oh yes. Uh uh uh constantly. And
>> there's a saying that says we are
learning until the day we die.
>> Thank you fellows.
>> Really appreciate that.
>> Thank you Daniel. Um, this good of you
to set this up.
>> Yep. We'll uh talk about when to
schedule it next and looking forward to
people's questions. So, thanks again.
Bye.
>> All right. Great. Ciao.
>> Okay, it's over.
Very fun. Yeah.
Oh, it's cool. It's a wild topic.
Yeah.